The sound of a train running alongside a river
The color of sunflowers blooming facing down
The sunset becomes a striped border
Why do I want to cry every time you say "thank you"?
I'm like a child
I thought I'd left all my tears in the fridge
Red rover, red rover, send that girl right over
Goodbye, bystander
We keep walking
Even if at the end of this road isn't Heaven or anything like that
I just want to keep being with you and smiling together
Pride, wishes, and hope
I'll always have them just like you do
When you're scared, so scared, and becoming depressed
I'll protect you, I'll always protect you with everything I have
I promise you to your face
Torrent
（島田(しまだ) 開(かい)）さーて
桐山(きりやま)も来たことだし—
All right, now that Kiriyama has joined us,
shall we continue?
もっかい
さっきの続きをやろうか
今 ここの局面をおいてたんだ
This is how I set up the board.
（桐山(きりやま) 零(れい)）これは…
This is...
ああ　俺が去年 獅子王戦(ししおうせん)の
挑戦者決定トーナメントで—
Last year, in the Lion King challenger's tournament, this is what the board looked like when I lost.
落とした一局なんだけど
何か 急に気になってな
For some reason, I couldn't get it out of my mind.
Tokyo
Nagano
Tokushima
Kyoto
今週末から徳島だからな
This weekend, I have to head to Tokushima.
自分の負け戦を—
So I felt like delving into one of my defeats.
ほじくり返して
みたくなったってわけさ
じゃあ 続きから…
All right, let's continue.
（二海堂(にかいどう)晴信(はるのぶ)）だ〜か〜ら
先手６一角(かく)　後手５二歩(ふ)
I'm telling you.
Black should go B-6a, and white should go P-5b.
Then black should go P-7d.
で 先手７四歩でいいんだってば！
Wrong. Black just needs to do P-7d.
（重田(しげた)盛夫(もりお)）
違う 単に先手７四歩だよ
何 そこで角打つ必要あんの？
ふふふ…
Why does the bishop need to be captured?
Are you the type who gets killed on a battlefield right away from moving around too much?
ひょっとして お前—
戦場で 無駄に動いて
すぐ死ぬタイプ？
Pffft
Pfft
What are you talking about?
はあ？ 何 言っちゃってんすか？
重田さんこそ 何すか？
What about you, Shigeta?
偉そうにどっかり構えて
状況確認ばっかりして—
You sit there with pride while
constantly checking the situation,
and before you know it, you're surrounded. The end!
気が付いたら周り囲まれて
ジ･エンド系？
Are you like Shimazu in the Battle of Sekigahara?
関ヶ原で言ったら島津系？
先手６一角に後手５二歩なら
つらいっしょ？
If black does B-6a, and white does P-5b,
it'll just make things worse.
６一角が打ち得！
The bishop at 6a being captured is a plus.
Whoever takes a bishop first will degenerate.
（重田）先に打った角がボケる
Black going with P-7d is logical.
単に 先手７四歩と突くのが
筋だっつの
先手７四歩に後手６四金(きん)なら
そこで先手６一角は筋違い
If black goes P-7d and G-6d, it's illogical to go with B-6a.
It makes more sense to go P-3e to capture your bishop at 7a.
先手３五歩から後手７一角の方が
筋がいいってんだよ
Rumble Rumble Rumble
Rumble Rumble
What? So you'll leave my pawn at 5b alone with your rook at 5h open?
Chuckle
はあ？
後手５二歩と打たせれば—
先手５八飛(ひ)の回りが
将来 味がいいんじゃないですか？
Their future sure looks bright.
Well then, how about my bishop at 6a captures your gold at 6d?
じゃあさ
６一角 後手６四金なら？
What? There's no way you'd approach my gold when you can't even capture the pawn at 7d!
*This conversation might be hard to follow, so we're providing metaphorical images as accompaniment.
はあ？ 先手が
７四歩も突いてないのに—
金(きん)を寄るなんて
あるわけないじゃないっすか
If you let me capture your pawn at 5b, I've already won.
後手５二歩を受けさせて必勝！
先手７四歩に４七角なら
どうするんですか？
How about the bishop at 4g captures the pawn at 7d?
Just play P-5f, right?
先手５六歩と打ちゃいいじゃん
What? You don't even get that?
何？ お前
そんなことも分かんないの？
Why don't you start over from 1-dan?
初段から出直せば？
Checkmate within 45 moves
Captured Piece(s):
Silver
Silence...
はー やっと静かになった
They've finally quieted down.
Stare
Checkmate within 7 moves
*Trick to quiet down hyper students in a classroom
So this method still works, huh?
まだ効くんだな この手
Once you've solved it, take your seat.
（講師）
解いたら席に着けよ！
で… 桐山はどう思う これ
So what do you think about this, Kiriyama?
Sorry?
はい？
お前は ６一角 打つ？
Would you go for the B-6a play?
Or the P-7d play?
それとも 単に７四歩でいく？
The thing is, at this point...
（零）というか これはもう…
この局面になった時点で
よくないのではないかと
Once the board gets to this position, you're already in bad shape.
What?
はあ？ 前提を崩すなよ
Don't undermine the premise.
We can't learn anything that way, Kiriyama.
研究にならないだろうが 桐山
But unless we imagine it in the context of a real match,
there's no point in studying it.
（零）あ でも…
本番を想定しないと
研究自体 意味が…
だとしたら この局面に
たどり着く前に何とかしないと
Something would have to be done before the board got to this point.
Be specific. How do you figure this is hopeless?
（重田）具体的に言えよ
これが そんな
ダメ筋だっていう理由をさ
えっ 説明って…
You mean explain it?
Um, how can I put it?
えーと 何ていうか…
It's disturbing, or like...
気持ち悪いっていうか…
えっ？ 気持ち悪い？
Disturbing?
What?
はぁ？ 気持ち悪い？
Disturbing?
Did you want to say something abstract and thought we'd interpret it as genius?
桐山 てめえ
抽象的に言っとけば
天才ぽいかなとか思って—
適当にしゃべってんじゃ
ねえだろうな
Speak clearly! Or do you want me to stimulate your speech center?
はっきり言えよ！
言語中枢の発達
促してやろうか？
Hey, put my cactus down.
（島田）おい
俺のサボテンを下におろせ！
Sorry, Kiriyama.
すまん 桐山
This is a workshop, so verbalize your feelings for us.
研究会だからな 言語化してくれ
今までは 一人研究だったから—
Until now, you studied alone,
so I'm sure you didn't bother with that.
その辺 すっ飛ばして
きたんだろうが
But do your best, and go ahead.
頑張って
はい どうぞ
えーっと まず…
Um, first...
３七の銀が残っている…
There's still a silver at 3g.
That's one thing I find disturbing.
…っていうのが
もう 気持ち悪いっていうか
ふむ
で どんなふうに？
So, what about it do you find disturbing?
Um...
ああ… えーっと…
I think black playing P-7d will only result in harm.
先手の７四歩の筋は—
もう 傷になるだけじゃ
ないのかなって
Harm? No way! What're you talking about?
（二海堂）傷？
ねーよ　何 言ってんの？
Yeah. At this point, I agree with the steamed bun's opinion.
ああ この点では 俺も
その小龍包(しょうろんぽう)と同じ意見だな
ん？ 小龍包？
Huh? Steamed bun?!
What's that, you bastard?!
何だと 貴様！ ふんっ！
You wanna take this outside? That'd make my day!
外に出ろ？
望むところだ！
Damn it, it's noisy.
あっは… うるさい
Shush it, you guys.
黙れよ〜 お前ら
Or I'll grab my cactus.
ぶつよ〜
I see.
そうか 気持ち悪いか…
Disturbing, huh?
Interesting.
なるほどね
Well, see you next time.
（二海堂）じゃ 失礼しまーす
Yep. I'll check my schedule and give you a call.
（島田）おう　次は また
スケジュール見て連絡するわ
Okay!
（二海堂）はーい
（島田）ああ 桐山
Oh, Kiriyama.
Yes?
はい
お前さあ
あした あいてない？
Are you free tomorrow?
はい 学校が終われば
用事は特に…
Yes.
I don't have any plans for after school.
"Can you come back tomorrow?
（零）
“もう一度 来てくれないか
今度は お前一人で”
This time, just you."
そう 島田さんは言った
That's what Shimada asked me.
And so, the next day...
そして 翌日
Hey there.
よーっす
Sorry to make you come two days in a row.
悪いな 連日
Wobble
You haven't slept?
寝てないんですか？
I have.
寝た
Or more like, I passed out.
…つか 気を失ってた
At the board.
盤に突っ伏して…
桐山 何飲む？
What do you want to drink, Kiriyama?
I'll take care of it. What would you like?
（零）ああ 僕がやります
何がいいですか？
Oh.
（島田）ああ…
じゃあ コーヒー 熱いの
I'll have some hot coffee, then.
I only have instant, though.
インスタントしかないけど
Here you are.
（零）はい どうぞ
（島田）ん… 悪いね
I appreciate it.
One more loss and the next one will be do-or-die.
あと一局落としたら もう角番だ
Losing in straight sets...
ストレート負けはな…
That's the one thing I want to avoid.
それだけはな…
I shouldn't have been wondering if I get to play in my hometown or not.
ふるさと うんぬん
言ってる場合じゃなかったな
First, I need to win twice.
まず ２勝だ
The sixth match is in my hometown.
六局目が 俺のふるさとなんだ
Um, your hometown...
あの ふるさとって？
ん？ ああ 山形だよ
It's Yamagata.
Yamagata...
山形…
What's it like?
どんな所ですか？
ああ… 雪しかない
It's just snow.
What about when there's no snow?
雪のないときは？
Mountains, rivers, rice paddies...
山と川と田んぼと…
うん 何にもないな
Yeah, nothing.
But if there are rice paddies, that's not nothing.
でも 田んぼがあるなら
何もなくは…
ああ でも 減反でな
But they're reducing the acreage, so even now, those rice paddies...
その田んぼも今じゃ…
…つーか
こんなこと言ってもあれだな
Well, it's not like you'll really get it with how I'm explaining things.
分かんないよな
ほんとに 何も
なくなろうとしてる所だよ
Basically, it's a place that doesn't want anything there.
That goes for people, rice paddies...
人も… 田んぼも…
Schools, homes...
学校も… 家も…
だから…
That's why...
That's exactly why...
だからこそ…
I couldn't hear what he said, but...
（零）聞き取れなかった
でも“だからこそ”と…
I have a feeling he said, "That's exactly why."
言ったような気がした
So, shall we get started?
さあ 始めようか
Go ahead and build the fortress normally.
普通に 矢倉(やぐら)をやってくれ
You remember the board from yesterday, right?
昨日の局面は覚えているな？
Like that.
あんな感じで…
Here we go.
いくぞ
K-8h.
P-9e.
（零）９五歩
R-3h.
（島田）３八飛
Wh-What is this?
（零）な 何だ！
N-7c.
７三桂(けい)
P-1f.
（島田）１六歩…
B-4b.
（零）４二角…
S-3g.
（零）５三銀…
S-5c.
（島田）３五…
P-3e.
It's rushing toward me.
（零）流れ込んでくる…
Px3e.
Shimada's thoughts are rushing toward me.
島田さんの思考が
Like water that's been let loose from a dam.
ダムが放水を始めたように
So suddenly,
いきなり こんな…
and with so much force!
なんて圧力…
B-3e.
（島田）３五角…
Bx3e.
（零）同角…
P-4c.
（島田）４三歩…
（零）うっ！ くはっ…！
ゲホ ゲホッ…
やべ… 寝てた
Crap! I was asleep.
し… 死ぬとこだった
I-I could've died.
That's right.
そか…
I came home.
帰ってきて…
イテッ…
Ow!
My shoulder and my eyes?
肩と目と…
What is this?
何だこれ…
I'm totally exhausted.
すげえ 疲れた…
（零）考えてみれば—
If I think about it, it was the first time I was subjected
Ａ級棋士の思考を 長時間…
モロに受け止めたのは
初めてだった
to a Class A player's thoughts for several hours.
まるで… 濁流のようだった
It was like a muddy stream.
でも 流されたり—
But I wouldn't let myself be swept away or retreat,
後ずさることだけは
してはいけないと…
so I held on desperately.
必死に ふんばった
（零）僕は…
いや 僕たちはプロだ
I'm...
No, we're both professionals.
どちらかだけが一方的に—
It's not a relationship where just one person is allowed to benefit.
甘い汁をすする
関係であってはならないのだ
あのとき 島田さんは—
At that time,
Shimada thought I had something that he could steal,
which is why he invited me.
僕から奪えるものがあると
思ったから僕を誘い—
And though possibly minor, I thought I had something to offer, and that's why I asked to join the workshop.
僕もまた 僅かかもしれないが—
差し出せるものがあると
思ったから—
研究会に入れてほしいと口にした
だから あの日…
突き刺さるように思った
Because on that day, a thought had pierced my mind.
僕は この人に
聞きたいことがある
"There's something I want to ask him."
カハッ！ はあー
Until I get that answer, all I can do is hang on.
（零）それをつかめるまでは—
絶対に 食い下がるしかないんだ
All right.
よし！
（零）翌日 島田さんは
徳島へ旅立った
The next day,
Shimada left to Tokushima.
獅子王戦 第三局の
幕が上がろうとしていた
The curtain was about to lift on the third match of the Lion King Tournament.
Torrent
Passing Time
Report Card
You just barely made it, huh?
（林田(はやしだ)高志(たかし)）ギリッギリ
セーフってとこだったな
（零）あ… 先生
Mr. Hayashida.
I guess everyone's going to Mouseland in two days for an End-of-Year party.
何か みんな あさって—
お別れ会で
ネズミーランドに行くらしいぜ
Did you know about it?
お前 知ってた？
Although I wasn't invited, of course.
もちろん 俺は
誘われてないけどね ハハ…
I don't know why you keep informing me of these things throughout the year.
（零）だから 何で
わざわざ知らせるんだと—
この一年間 何回も
言ってきましたよね
I really think this falls into the realm of bullying.
これってもう…
もはや イジメの域だと
思うんですよね 僕
Seriously?
Come on...
Nothing has changed.
（零）何も 変わりませんでした
I squeaked by with attendance.
出席もギリギリで 部活も入らず
I didn't join a club.
I didn't get promoted, either.
順位戦も停滞して…
I haven't accomplished anything.
何の成果も出せなかったけれど
But I was able to move up a grade because of...
でも 進級できたことは
先生の…
Because of you, Mr. Hayashida.
先生のおかげです
Thank you.
ありがとうございました
Come on, now.
よせよ
成果がなかったなんて…
そんなこと言うなよ
Haven't accomplished anything?
Don't say that.
You've been coming to school while working.
働きながら 学校にも通って
You cook for yourself.
自分で飯作って 洗濯して
ゴミとか出して
You do the laundry and take out the trash.
You compete.
戦って
You make money and pay rent.
お金稼いで 家賃払って
俺が17歳のころは—
When I was 17, I thought,
"I can be a big shot when I grow up."
もしかしたら 結構自分は—
すごいやつに
なるんじゃないかなんて
I had that baseless dream while going to the arcade,
reading manga, hanging out with friends, watching TV...
根拠のない夢とか見ながら—
ゲーセン行ったり 漫画読んだり
友達と遊んだり テレビ見たり
I never worried about rent or bothered to save up money.
家賃の心配も
貯金もしたことなかった
I never cleaned or cooked or did the laundry.
掃除も 飯の支度も
洗濯もしたことなかった
Takashi! I need
to vacuum!
So don't tell me you haven't accomplished anything.
何も成果がなかったなんて
言うなよ！
You did your best!
頑張ってたよ！
I saw it!
俺は見てたよ！
I want him to stop.
（零）やめてほしい
He's always like this.
この人は いつだってそうだ
無神経にズバズバと
Insensitive and outspoken...
I just wish he'd stop.
ほんと やめてほしい
When he suddenly says this sort of stuff,
こんなふうに いきなりは…
I can't handle it.
ほんと… 困るんだ
（零）くっ ううっ…
（林田）なあ まだ冷えんな
Hey, it's still cold outside, right?
How about we go for some oden?
おでんでも食いに行かねーか？
My treat, to celebrate you moving up a grade.
おごるぞ 進級祝いに
That's okay. You don't...
（零）いいですよ そんな…
Then do you wanna go to Mouseland?
（林田）んじゃ 行くか？
ネズミーランド 男二人で！
Just us two guys!
You wanna go right now?
行っちゃうのか？ これから！
No, oden is...
（零）いえ おでんで…
Really, oden is good.
いえ ほんと おでんで…
And so,
（零）そして
僕の短い春休みが始まった
my short spring break began.
The Lion King Tournament, match three, day two.
獅子王戦 第三局 ２日目
Lion King Tournament Live Feed
S-6f
P-6e
Sx6e
R-5e
L-6f
B-4f
S-6f
P-6e
Sx6e
R-5e
L-6f
B-4f
Shimada is in a tight spot.
島田さん 苦しい…
At this rate, all he can do is persevere.
このままでは
粘り続けるしか手がないか
Lion King Tournament Live Feed
S-6f
P-6e
Sx6e
R-5e
L-6f
B-4f
S-6f
P-6e
Sx6e
R-5e
L-6f
B-4f
しかも… 島田さんの
消費時間の方が多い
On top of that, he's expended more time.
One more loss and the next one will be do-or-die.
あと一局落としたら もう角番だ
Losing in straight sets...
ストレート負けはな…
That's the one thing I don't want.
それだけはな…
Shimada, please... Please...
（零）島田さん　どうか どうか…
（零）あ は〜い
Coming!
誰だ？
Who could that be?
Hina, and Momo too.
ヒナちゃん　モモちゃんも…
（川本(かわもと)ひなた）え〜と…
おっ お重箱を取りにきました！
Um, w-we came to pick up our empty boxes.
Tiny
Glance
Um, hold on a second.
え〜と ちょっと待ってて
今 何か飲むものを
I'll get you something to drink.
What should I serve guests?
（零）お客さんって
何を出したらいいんだ？
I'm sure tea would be fine for adults,
but what do I serve a junior high student and a kindergartner?
大人なら
お茶とかでいいんだろうけど—
中学生と園児って
何を出したらいいんだ？
You have hot tea with fried tofu pouches!
In a sense, relatively easy to serve as a guest...
（幸田(こうだ)香子(きょうこ)）
おいなりさんには
あっついお茶でしょ！
チョコないの？
Don't you have any chocolate? Serve me something sweet!
何か甘いもの出してよ！
コーラないのーっ？
You don't have any soda?!
Um, thank you for the multi-tiered box of food.
（零）あの…
お重箱 ありがとう
It was delicious.
おいしかったです
Did you eat all of it?
桐山君 ちゃんと食べた？
I-I did.
た… 食べたよ
Nom
Though she ate most of it...
（零）ほとんど
食べられちゃったけど
Nom
I managed to have two pieces.
辛うじて２個は…
Um, the one with wasabi was really good.
えーっと
わさびのがおいしかった
I see. That's good to hear.
そっかあ よかった
Sis and I made that together.
おねいちゃんと二人で作ったんだ
It turned out really well for Girls' Day Festival, so we made some for you too.
おひな祭りに作って
おいしかったから—
零ちゃんにもって
Grandpa likes wasabi, so we put that in for him.
わさび味のは—
おじいちゃんが好きだから
入れてみたんだ
かぷっ ぐっ… ぐっ…
ふひゅー　ぷはー！
…で
So...
When we last saw you,
こないだの… あの人 誰！
who was that person with you?!
ブアシッ！
Um... from then?
Stare
あっ その… こないだの？
えっと 何ていうの… その…
Um, how can I put it?
Uh...
I was wondering if you were all right.
零ちゃん 大丈夫かな？ って…
え… えーと
U-Um, because it looked like you were arguing with her.
ケ… ケンカしてたみたいだし
I mean, it seemed like you were on the receiving end...
というか…
何か 一方的に
やられたっぽく見えてたから
S-So I wondered if you were okay, and...
だ 大丈夫なのかなって その…
I-Is she a witch?
（川本モモ）ま 魔女なの？
（香子）ほんとに魔女なら…
If I really were a witch,
I wouldn't be dealing with these pathetic problems.
こんな情けない苦労してない
No.
違う… 違うよ
No, she's not.
She's no witch.
魔女なんかじゃない
彼女は 僕の姉さんだよ
She's my...
older sister.
Older sister?
おねいさん？
Yeah.
そうだよ きょうだいだもの
ケンカだってするよ
We're family, so sometimes we fight.
But it's all right.
でも大丈夫　きょうだいだもの
Because we're siblings.
It's the same at your house, right, Momo?
モモちゃんちも そうでしょ？
That's true! Akari and Hina are always fighting!
そういえば—
あかりおねいちゃんも
ヒナちゃんも いっぱいケンカする
バカーって 泣いたりしてる
She really cries a lot!
わぁー こら！ モモー！
Hey! Momo!
But they're still really close!
でもね 仲良し！
Yeah.
そうだよ
That's what I mean.
（ひなた）ただいまー！
We're home!
Mystery solved!
分かったよー！
Sis, that woman is Rei's sister!
お姉ちゃん あの人ね—
零ちゃんの おねいさんだった！
（川本あかり）あ…
（ひなた）よかった よかった
What a relief!
心配して損しちゃった
I was worried over nothing.
It was just an argument between siblings.
ただの きょうだいゲンカ
だったんだよ〜
Who would've figured?
な〜んだ もう
Is that so?
（あかり）へー
（モモ）エヘッ
Huh...
そうなんだ
ふぅーん
Oh no...
Wait, Hina, that's probably worse!
（あかり）…ってひな
そっちの方がまずいってば
Oh no...
（シロちゃん）ああ… 暖かい
Heap
So warm.
Cozy
（ミケちゃん）ここ最高
This is the best.
Let's watch Squirrely Teacher!
「リスポッケ先生」見よう！
Yeah, let's watch Squirrely Teacher!
よーし「リスポッケ先生」
見ようっと
（クロちゃん）
おなかがすいたんです！
I'm hungry!
Teach us, Squirrely Teacher!
Squirrely Teacher! Squirrely Teacher!
I'm hungry!
Mreow
おなかがすいたんです！
そんな リスなんていいから
Never mind that squirrel!
Mreow
In fact, I'm so hungry, I could eat that squirrel!
…っていうか もう むしろ
リスでもいいから食べさせて！
Squirrely Teacher, please teach us something!
Mreow
*You shouldn't eat squirrels.
He knows everything.
While eating some nuts...
（あかり）
一つ屋根の下に 10年近く…
They lived under the same roof for almost ten years.
なのに あの時の二人からは—
But when we saw them together,
ほんの少しだって—
they didn't seem at all like brother and sister.
きょうだいのにおいなんて
してこなかった
I see. Rei...
そうか… 零君
だから あなたは
その家を出たのね
So that's why...
you left that house, isn't it?
（零）獅子王戦 第三局
In the third match of the Lion King Tournament, after 113 moves, Shimada Kai, 8-dan...
113手目にして…
島田開八段　投了
conceded.
そして ５時になり
And at 5 o'clock, I heard a familiar tune being broadcast throughout town.
町じゅうに
遠く懐かしい曲が流れ…
僕は今日 初めてその曲が—
For the first time, I noticed that song is called "Hometown."
「ふるさと」だと 気が付いた…
Passing Time
Your fingers, your chest, your eyes
Are so dazzling there are nights when I get dizzy
They suddenly fall upon me, and it's just so warm
That it feels like I swallowed a seven-colored star
You held me tight, troubling me like a burning spark would
But I was taught to keep walking despite everything
God, please hear me out
For just a little while
Please connect us like that constellation
So that we're never away from each other
So that we're always together
Next Episode Preview
Episode 19
（零）宗谷(そうや)名人(めいじん)って
どんな人なんですか？
What's Master Souya like?
He really does piss me off.
（島田）ほ〜んと あいつ
ムカつきますよね〜
Like how his skin is so shiny,
or how fluffy he is...
いつまでもピチピチっつうか
フサフサっつうか
（零）あの… 島田さん
Um, Shimada,
I'm going home for today.
僕 今日はこれで帰ります
Illustration: Aoki Ume
（あかり）せーの
Three, two, one...
Don't miss the next episode of
"March comes in like a lion"!
（あかり･ひなた･モモ）
３月のライオン
次回もお楽しみに！
（ひなた）リスポッケ先生の
好きなものって何だろうね？
I wonder what Squirrely Teacher likes to eat.
Bubble gum!
（モモ）ガム！